Guide to the Washington Office on Latin America Records, 1962-2020 and undated, bulk 1974-2005; 1962-ongoing RL.01401
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Geographic Series, 1962-2008 and undated, 250 boxes
  - Mexico, 1988-2008 and undated, 44 boxes
    - Printed Material, 1994-2008
      Various items published by Mexican activist groups and U.S. government. Includes a nearly complete five-year run, 1994-1999, of Proceso, a Mexican magazine focusing on politics.
      - Autogestion, 1997-2000, 3 folders (Box 227)
      - Academia Mexicana de Derechos Humanos, 1997 (Box 227)
      - Borderlines, 2000-2002 (Box 227)
      - Camino a la masacre, 1998 (Box 227)
      - CATO Institute, Willing Workers: Fixing the Problem of Illegal Mexican Migration to the United States, 2002 (Box 227)
      - Center for Strategic and International Studies, New Horizons in U.S.-Mexico Relations, 2001 (Box 227)
      - Centro de Derechos Humanos Fray Bartolomé de las Casas, 1996-2000, 1-3 of 5 folders (Box 227)
      - Centro de Derechos Humanos Fray Bartolomé de las Casas, 1996-2000, 4-5 of 5 folders (Box 228)
      - Centro de Derechos Humanos Fray Francisco de Vitoria OP, A.C., 2003-2004 (Box 228)
      - Centro de Derechos Humanos de Montaña, 1997-2005, 3 folders (Box 228)
      - Centro de Derechos Humanos Tepeyac, 1997 (Box 228)
      - Centro de Estudios Fronterizos, 1998, 2 folders (Box 228)
      - Comisión de Defensa de los Derechos Humanos del Estado Guerrero, undated (Box 228)
      - Comisión de Derechos Humanos de Distrito Federal, 2003 (Box 228)
      - Comisión Mexicana de Defensa y Promoción de los Derechos Humanos, 1999-2000 (Box 229)
      - Compromisos Quebrantados y Justicia Aplazada, undated (Box 229)
      - Contraste, La Tortura, 2001 (Box 229)
      - Cosyddhac: Inventario de Vida, 1994 (Box 229)
      - De Ciudadano a Ciudadano, 1997 (Box 229)
      - Los Cuidadanos y el Poder Judicial Federal, undated (Box 229)
      - Desafio al Derecho de Asociación en Mexico y America Latina, 1999 (Box 229)
      - Defensor, 2006-2008, 2 folder (Box 229)
      - Excluded People, Eroded Communities, 2006 (Box 229)
      - La Experiencia Entre la Delegación y los Comites Vecinales, 2000 (Box 229)
      - FEMOSPP [Fiscal Especial para Movimientos Sociales y Politicos del Pasado], 2003 (Box 229)
      - Global Exchange, Foreigners of Conscience: the Mexican Government's Campaign Against International Human Rights Observers in Chiapas, 2001 (Box 229)
      - Global Exchange human rights delegation to Chiapas, 1995 (Box 229)
      - Human rights report, 2006 (Box 229)
      - Human Rights Watch, Military Injustice: Mexico's Failure to Punish Army Abuses, 2001 (Box 229)
      - ICCHRLA [Inter-Church Committee on Human Rights in Latin America] report, 1995 (Box 229)
      - Iglesias, 1998, 2 monthly issues in 1 folder (Box 230)
      - Incide Social, Agendas Cuidadanas, 2007 (Box 230)
      - Informe sobre la Situación de los Derechos Economicos, Sociales, y Culturos, 2003 (Box 230)
      - Interhemispheric Resource Center, The Clinton Administration and the Mexican Elections, 1994 (Box 230)
      - International Republican Institute, Mexico election observation report, 2000 (Box 230)
      - Latin American Working Group, Troubling Patterns: The Mexican Military and the War on Drugs, undated (Box 230)
      - Mexican Academy of Human Rights, 1999 (Box 230)
      - Mexico-U.S. Advocates Network, 2001, English and Spanish versions of May 2001 issue in 1 folder (Box 230)
      - Militarización y Violencia en Chiapas, undated (Box 230)
      - Minnesota Advocates for Human Rights, 1996 (Box 230)
      - National Democratic Initiatives, Media Objectivity in Mexico, 1997 (Box 230)
      - Peace Brigades International/USA, PBI/USA Report, 2001 (Box 230)
      - Proceso, 1994-1995, 4 folders (Box 230)
      - Proceso, 1995-1997 (Box 231)
      - Proceso, 1998 (Box 232)
      - Proceso, 1999-2001 (Box 233)
      - Proceso, 2001, 2 folders (Box 234)
      - El Proceso de Guerra en Mexico, 1994-1999, 1999 (Box 234)
      - Proceso de Paz, Proceso de Guerra, 2003 (Box 234)
      - Proceduria General de Justicia del Distrito Federal, 1998-2000 (Box 234)
      - ProDH [Centro de Derechos Humanos Miguel Augustin pro Juarez, A.C.], Focus, 1999-2007 (Box 234)
      - ProDH [Centro de Derechos Humanos Miguel Augustin pro Juarez, A.C.], 1996-2007, 6 folders (Box 234)
      - Red Nacional de Organismos Civiles de Derechos Humanos, undated (Box 235)
      - ReVista: Harvard Review of Latin America, Mexico in Transition, 2001 (Box 235)
      - Rostros y Voces, 1996, 2 bi-monthly issues in 1 folder (Box 235)
      - SIPAZ Report, 2001-2002, 4 monthly issues in 1 folder (Box 235)
      - Strategic Studies Institute, 1994, 2006 (Box 235)
      - Tortura en Mexico, 2000 (Box 235)
      - WOLA reports, 2001, 2003, 2 folders (Box 235)
      - University of California, Berkeley, Center for Latin American Studies, 2002, single issue on Mexico (Box 235)
      - Woodrow Wilson Center, 2001-2002 (Box 235)
    - U.S. Relations, 1991-1999 and undated, 9 folders (Box 235)
      Materials chiefly concern U.S. politics, responses in the U.S. press to events in Mexico, and immigration and shared-border issues.
    - WOLA Files, 1988, 1991-1997 and undated (Box 236-238)
      Administrative files maintained by WOLA staff contain contact lists; planning materials for conferences, working groups, and visits from Mexican delegations and other individuals; correspondence; reprints of published articles; and other materials. Four folders of materials document in detail WOLA's role as co-coordinator of series of Washington roundtables on Mexico in 1994 and 1995: roundtables focused on Chiapas, drug trafficking, and process of democratic reform. Includes a folder of readings used by participants to prepare for sessions.
  - Nicaragua, 1984-2006 and undated, 8 boxes
    Chiefly concerns Nicaraguan politics and government. Files in this subseries do not directly address the 1979 revolution or its immediate aftermath, but to later events. Key topics include elections in 1990, 1996, and 2001; peace negotiations between the Nicaraguan state and rebel groups, and some assessments of the United States' role in Nicaraguan political affairs. Files are separated into the following folder groups: Human Rights, Peace Process, Politics and Government, Printed Material, and WOLA Files. Most files in Human Rights refer to abuses committed during hostilities between the ruling Sandinista (Frente Sandinista de Liberación Nacional, FSLN) government and the various counter insurgent groups commonly called "Contras." Reports on the FSLN's treatment of political dissidents also appear here. Peace Process files include copies of accords negotiated to end the Contra War as well as reports by international observers. The largest grouping, Politics and Government contains clippings, reports, and government documents related to national elections and constitutional law. Major election observers include the International Human Rights Law Group (IHRLG) and Hemisphere Initiatives. Printed Material focuses on Nicaraguan politics and government as well as human rights and includes a mostly complete run of Barricada Internacional from July 1993-September 1996. Finally, WOLA Files consist of correspondence and draft reports by WOLA and partner organizations attempting to influence U.S. policy towards Nicaragua. U.S.-Nicaraguan relations are a major component of this grouping, and some discussion of the role of the CIA in the Contra War can be found here. Files in this grouping document WOLA's efforts to influence policy as the shifting political climate of each presidential administration created different circumstances. Because the Contra War was international in nature, researchers interested in this subject are encouraged to consult subseries on Costa Rica and Honduras as well. Videocassette on Nicaraguan sweatshops and property rights can be found at the end of the subseries.
    - Human Rights, 1986-2001, undated (Box 239)
    - Peace Process, 1987-1991, undated (Box 239-240)
    - Politics and Government, 1986-2001 (Box 240-243)
    - Printed Material, 1984-2006, undated
      - Auditoria de la Democracia Nicaragua, 1999 (Box 243)
      - Barricada International, 1993-1996, 3 folders (Box 243)
      - CENIDH [Centro Nicaragüense de Derechos Humanos]: Derechos Humanos en Nicaragua, 2002 (Box 243)
      - Diretorio ONG de Nicaragua, 1995 (Box 243)
      - Hurricane Mitch sustainable development executive summary, 1999 (Box 243)
      - The Miskito Question and the Revolution in Nicaragua, 1984 (Box 243)
      - Nicaragua travel handbook, undated (Box 243)
      - Observatoria Legislativo, 2006 (Box 243)
    - WOLA Files, 1985-2003 and undated (Box 243-246)
  - Panama, 1988-2000 and undated, 4 boxes
    Files cover typical issues found in other series such as human rights abuses and reforms, politics and government, the economy, U.S. relations, and international relations. Specific topics include the Panama Canal, U.S. congressional activities, the 1989 U.S. invasion of Panama and the trial of Manuel Noriega; drug policies and police forces in Panama; and the Catholic Church. Folders of information on human rights cases and organizations include analyses, conference reports, commentaries, and testimony. Main language is English although there are documents in Spanish from Panama. One folder contains a set of FBIS reports on Panama (the Foreign Broadcast Information Service is a U.S. government operation that monitors and translates news, speeches, broadcasts, and commentary from non-English sources around the world).
    - Panama files (Box 247-250)
  - Paraguay, 1971-2001 and undated, 7 boxes
    Arranged in the following groupings of files: Background Files, which contain clippings, notes, and articles on such issues as the economy, elections, U.S. and other relations (Japan, South Africa), land issues, culture, energy, and the military; Clippings, files created by WOLA staff on a range of topics and events; Elections, containing information on 1989 and 1991 national and municipal elections; Human Rights, with information on human rights abuses, cases, trials, the judiciary, and organizations (the latter is arranged in alphabetical order and includes Amnesty International, America Watch, Centre de Documentation Paysanne du Paraguay, and several labor organizations); Politics and Government, with extensive files on U.S. relations and aid, particularly focused on the congressional record (approximately 1976-1985) and U.S. Ambassador Clyde Taylor's role, as well as files on the Paraguayan government's structure and activities; and Publications and Other Printed Material, a variety of analyses and articles, including WOLA's own Decline of the Dictator: Paraguay at a Crossroads, 1988; and one box of printed material, chiefly reports on Paraguayan human rights and politics-indexed by title below. Many materials in the Paraguay series are in Spanish but the majority are in English. Particular topics covered in the Human Rights files include land reform, peasants, and labor issues. Several runs of grassroots publications are found in the Human Rights files, notably a set of issues of Revista Mbya (1993-1995), a voice for indigenous peoples, especially the Mbya of eastern Paraguay.
    - Background Files, 1971-1990 and undated (Box 251)
    - Clippings, 1989-1999 (Box 221-252)
    - Elections, 1988-1991 (Box 252)
    - Human Rights, 1987-2001 and undated (Box 252-254)
    - Politics and Government, 1974-1998 (bulk 1989-1990) (Box 254-255)
    - Publications and Other Printed Material, 1984-1991 (Box 255-257)
  - Perú, 1982-2003 and undated, 21 boxes
    Files in this subseries are generally related to the administration of Alberto Fujimori (1990-2000) and responses to it by human rights groups in Perú as well as associated solidarity groups in the United States. Most are concerned with efforts of groups, chiefly WOLA, to raise awareness or encourage action on human rights abuses attributed to the Fujimori regime. The vast majority of material was created or collected by longtime WOLA associate and fellow Coletta Youngers. Researchers interested in human rights in Perú are encouraged to consult the Coletta Youngers Papers, 1977-2004 and undated, housed in the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library at Duke. Subseries is divided into the following folder groups: Articles and Reports; Conferences and Programs; Correspondence and Memoranda; Human Rights Organizations and Cases; Politics and Government; and Visits and U.S. Policy.
    - Articles and Reports, 1982-2003, undated (Box 258-259)
      Contains drafts and copies of op-eds and letters to editors, press releases, and reports published by WOLA and WOLA-affiliated personnel.
    - Conferences and Programs, 1989-2002, undated (Box 259-263)
      Consists of files related to conferences, seminars, and other events in which Coletta Youngers or other WOLA staff participated. Most of these were organized by WOLA, often in conjunction with the George Washington University's Latin American Studies Program.
    - Correspondence and Memoranda, 1991-1999, undated (Box 264-265)
      Grouping contains a mix of letters to state officials in Perú, including Alberto Fujimori, as well as those in the United States, chiefly members of Congress and Secretaries of State James Baker and Madeleine Albright. In addition, internal communications between WOLA staff and associated colleagues and memoranda about recent activities are also included.
    - Human Rights Organizations and Cases, 1986-2003, undated (Box 266-272)
      The largest grouping, files are further separated into Coordinadora Nacional de Derechos Humanos (CNDDH), the Perú Peace Network (PPN), and Other Organizations and Cases. The CNDDH is an umbrella human rights organization based in Lima, Perú that organizes and helps coordinate the activities of over fifty human rights groups working in Perú and is one of WOLA's primary partners in Perú. The PPN is a Missouri-based solidarity organization with which WOLA is affiliated. Other groups represented in this section include the Asociacion Pro Derechos Humanos (APRODEH), Defensoria del Pueblo, Amnesty International, and Americas Watch. Specific cases include files on human rights advocate and Partido Democrático Descentralista co-founder Javier Diez Canseco; the 1997 Japanese Embassy hostage crisis; lawsuits filed against Texaco for environmental damage in Perú; Peruvian army intelligence officer and alleged torturer Tomas Ricardo Anderson Kohatsu; and the massacre at Los Barrios Altos.
    - Politics and Government, 1991-2003, undated (Box 272-275)
      Files refer to the political situation internal to Perú. Topics of note in this grouping include the Democratic Constitutional Congress initiated by Fujimori in 1992, some files on Peruvian drug policy, decrees issued by Fujimori, the 1995 border conflict with Ecuador, elections in 1990 and 2000, and the Truth and Reconciliation Commission convened after Fujimori fled Perú in 2000.
    - Visits and U.S. Policy, 1987-2003, undated (Box 275-278)
      Concern efforts to influence Peruvian human rights policy outside Perú. The bulk of the grouping details WOLA's efforts to organize meetings between members of Peruvian congress or human rights advocates and U.S. officials. Approximately one box of material relates specifically to visits by members of Coordinadora Nacional de Derechos Humanos. General files on U.S. policy towards Perú appear at the end of the grouping. These include files on congressional debates in the 1990s over whether to continue funding the Peruvian government's anti-narcotics programs in light of evidence of widespread human rights abuses.
  - Suriname, 1997
    One folder on Suriname's proposed truth and reconciliation commission. Includes a letter of support for this process from WOLA and paperwork for adding signatories. Information on Suriname's political background germane to the truth and reconciliation commission can be found at back of the file.
    - Suriname files (Box 278)
  - Uruguay, 1976-1998 and undated, 4 boxes
    Mainly concerned with political events and human rights issues that arose during Uruguay's transition from military to civilian rule in the 1980s. The subseries is separated into the following folder groups: Background and Issues, Cases, Political Parties, Printed Material, WOLA Files, and Other Material. The Background and Issues group contains some research about the political history of Uruguay, but it is mainly composed of files about issues contemporaneous with WOLA's work there in the 1980s, including elections, human rights, the military, the press, and the 1989 referendum on the "Ley de Caducidad de la Pretensión Punitiva del Estado" (granting amnesty for many human rights violations committed under the military dictatorship of 1973-1985). The Cases files comprise correspondence and research about the 1976 assassinations of Uruguayan politicians Zelmar Michelini and Héctor Gutiérrez Ruiz. The Political Parties folders contain printed materials about the Frente Amplio, the Partido Colorado, and various communist and socialist parties in Uruguay. Journals and newsletters from various NGOs make up the bulk of the Printed Material group; organizations and/or publications represented here include Aportes, CELADU (Centro de Estudios Para la Democracia Uruguaya), CLAEH (Centro Latinoamericano de Economía Humana), IELSUR (Instituto de Estudios Legales y Sociales del Uruguay), and SERPAJ (Servicio Páz y Justicia). The WOLA Files consist mainly of newsletters, press releases, and other publications generated by WOLA, but also include correspondence, contact lists, and other office files. Finally, documents gathered under Other Material include general correspondence, letters to the United States Congress, and a variety of printed material and reports about Uruguay's history, politics, and current events. Arranged mainly as received, in groups of color-coded files, except for Other Material, which consists of folders that were either too few to constitute a group or whose organizational theme could not be determined.
    - Background and Issues, 1978-1998 and undated (Box 279-280)
    - Cases, 1979-1988, 3 folders (Box 280)
    - Political Parties, 1982-1990 and undated (Box 280)
    - Printed Material, 1980-1994 and undated (Box 280-281)
    - WOLA Files, 1977-1989 and undated (Box 281-282)
    - Other Material, 1980-1998 and undated (Box 282)
  - Venezuela, 1995-2003 and undated, bulk 1995-1998
    Clippings, files and printed material on human rights, politics, and economic policy in Venezuela. Several files chronicle Hugo Chavez's first presidential electoral victory as well as challenges to his administration from politically right-of-center opponents. Files on Venezuelan economic policy are included, particularly concerning loans from international financial institutions and the role of oil. Material from human rights organizations including Red de Apoyo, PROVEA, and the Comité de Familiares de Víctimas del 27 de Febrero (COFAVIC) comprise most of the rest of the subseries. One folder containing the WOLA publication Venezuela Update dated March 2003 begins the subseries.
    - Venezuela files (Box 283-284)
  - Latin America, 1982-2006 and undated
    Files pertaining to multiple geographic subseries. Divided into General Files and Printed Material. General Files include clippings on human rights, economic, and political issues across individual states. Some of these files address particular regions, including the Southern Cone and the Andes, while others refer to South America or Central America. As with the rest of the collection, most files are oriented around United States policy toward Latin America. However, the Interamerican Commission on Human Rights (IACHR) and the Organization of American States (OAS) figure more prominently in General Files. Conference and seminar-related documentation also appear in this group. Printed Material includes publications with the same broad scope as found in General Files. The largest component is a mostly complete run of Central America Report dated between 1985 and 1996. Other publications include a very early report by Americas Watch and numerous WOLA reports. Two boxes of printed material are unsorted. One videocassette, Peace, What Peace? Confronting Central America's New Economic War, produced by the Inter-Church Committee on Human Rights in Latin America (ICCHRLA), and one audio cassette on ex-combatants in El Salvador and Nicaragua complete the subseries. Additional audio recordings on Latin America may be found in the Sound Recordings Series.
    [Original audiovisual material closed to use. Technical Services staff may need to arrange to have viewing copy made. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.]
    - General Files, 1989-2000, undated (Box 284-288)
    - Printed Material, 1982-2006, undated
      - Americas Watch, first year report, 1982 (Box 289)
      - Central America Report, 1985-1996, 1-12 of 19 folders (Box 289)
      - Central America Report, 1985-1996, 13-19 of 19 folders (Box 290)
      - Envio, 1993, 1994 (Box 290)
      - IACHR, How to Petition the Interamerican System, undated (Box 290)
      - Inforpress Centroamericana, 1990-1991 (Box 290)
      - International Policy Report, 1991, undated (Box 290)
      - Kellogg Institute working papers, 1994-1995, 2 folders (Box 291)
      - This Week in Central America, 1992-1995, 2 folders (Box 291)
      - Various human rights reports, 1990, 2001 (Box 291)
      - WOLA, Cross Currents, 1999-2006, 2 folders (Box 291)
      - WOLA reports, 1986-2002, 2 folders (Box 291)
      - Unsorted printed material, 1985-2006 (Box 292-293)
- Initiatives and Activities Series, 1980-2008 and undated, 115 boxes
  Files documenting WOLA's issue-based work and activities in multiple countries. Separated into the following subseries: Advocacy Training Program, Conferences and Programs, Drug Policy, Hurricane Mitch, Legislative Files, Media Work, Rights and Development, and Security. The largest subseries are WOLA's longstanding programs on Drug Policy, Rights and Development, and Security. Initiatives and Activities files loosely mirror Geographic files in terms of structure, with the larger subseries divided into folder groups. As with other series, material has been rearranged only to the extent necessary to create folder groups. There is considerable overlap between materials in this series and those in other Geographical files; researchers looking into topics in Initiatives and Activities may wish to consult boxes in the country files as well.
  - Advocacy Training Program, 1995-2003 and undated, 9.5 boxes